I'm going to speak
سأقوم بالحديث
about a tiny, little idea.
حول فكرة بالغة الصغر.
And this is about shifting baseline.
وهذا يتعلق بخط الأساس المنزلق.
And because the idea can be explained in one minute,
ولأن الفكرة يمكن شرحها في دقيقة،
I will tell you three stories before
سأروي لكم ثلاث قصص قبل
to fill in the time.
لأملأ الوقت.
And the first story
والقصة الأولى
is about Charles Darwin, one of my heroes.
هي حول تشارلز داروين، أحد أبطالي.
And he was here, as you well know, in '35.
وقد كان هنا، كما تعلمون جيدا، في 35'.
And you'd think he was chasing finches,
وقد تظنون أنه كان يطارد العصافير،
but he wasn't.
لكنه لم يكن.
He was actually collecting fish.
كان في الواقع يجمع السمك.
And he described one of them
وقد وصف إحداها
as very "common."
على أنها "شائعة".
This was the sailfin grouper.
هذه كانت هامور السيلفين.
A big fishery was run on it
مصايد كبيرة للأسماك كانت تدور حولها
until the '80s.
إلى غاية الثمانينيات.
Now the fish is on the IUCN Red List.
والآن تتواجد السمكة على اللائحة الحمراء للاتحاد العالمي للحفاظ على الطبيعة.
Now this story,
الآن هذه القصة،
we have heard it lots of times
قد سمعناها مرات عديدة
on Galapagos and other places,
في غالاباغوس وأماكن أخرى،
so there is nothing particular about it.
وبالتالي ليس هناك أي شيء استثنائي بخصوصها.
But the point is, we still come to Galapagos.
لكن الفكرة هي أننا لا زلنا نأتي إلى غالاباغوس.
We still think it is pristine.
ولا نزال نعتقد أنها بكر.
The brochures still say
لاتزال المطوية تقول
it is untouched.
أنها غير ممسوسة.
So what happens here?
إذن ما الذي يحدث هنا؟
The second story, also to illustrate another concept,
القصة الثانية، تصور كذلك مفهوما آخر،
is called shifting waistline.
يسمى انزلاق محيط الخصر.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Because I was there in '71,
لأنني كنت هناك في 71'،
studying a lagoon in West Africa.
أدرس في لاغون في غرب إفريقيا.
I was there because I grew up in Europe
كنت هناك لأنني ترعرعت في أوروبا
and I wanted later to work in Africa.
وأردت أن أعمل لاحقا في إفريقيا.
And I thought I could blend in.
وظننت أنني قد أندمج.
And I got a big sunburn,
وحصلت على حروق شمس كبيرة،
and I was convinced that I was really not from there.
وكنت متيقنا أنني لست حقا من هناك.
This was my first sunburn.
كانت تلك أول حروق شمس لي.
And the lagoon
واللاغون
was surrounded by palm trees,
كان محاطا بأشجار النخيل،
as you can see, and a few mangrove.
كما يمكنكم أن تروا، وبعض المنغروف.
And it had tilapia
وكان فيها سمك البلطي
about 20 centimeters,
حوالي 20 سنتيمترا،
a species of tilapia called blackchin tilapia.
صنف من البلطي يدعى البلطي أسود الذقن.
And the fisheries for this tilapia
ومصايد الأسماك الخاصة بالبلطي
sustained lots of fish and they had a good time
قد قوى الكثير من الأسماك وقضت وقتا جيدا
and they earned more than average
وقد حصلوا على أكثر من المتوسط
in Ghana.
في غانا.
When I went there 27 years later,
حين ذهبت إلى هناك بعد 27 سنة،
the fish had shrunk to half of their size.
تقلصت الأسماك إلى نصف حجمها.
They were maturing at five centimeters.
كانت تنضج بخمس سنتيمترات.
They had been pushed genetically.
تم دفعها جينيا.
There were still fishes.
لا تزال أسماكا.
They were still kind of happy.
كانت لا تزال فرحة نوعا ما.
And the fish also were happy to be there.
والأسماك كانت كذلك فرحة بتواجدها هناك.
So nothing has changed,
وبالتالي لم يتغير شيء،
but everything has changed.
لكن تغير كل شيء.
My third little story
قصتي الصغيرة الثالثة
is that I was an accomplice
هي أنني كنت متواطئا
in the introduction of trawling
في إدخال الصيد بشباك الجر
in Southeast Asia.
في جنوب شرق آسيا.
In the '70s -- well, beginning in the '60s --
في السبعينيات -- حسنا، بداية في الستينيات --
Europe did lots of development projects.
قامت أوروبا بالكثير من المشاريع التنموية.
Fish development
تنمية الأسماك
meant imposing on countries
تعني إرغام الدول
that had already 100,000 fishers
التي كان لديها 100,000 سمكة مسبقا
to impose on them industrial fishing.
لفرض الصيد الصناعي عليهم.
And this boat, quite ugly,
وهذا المركب، قبيح جدا،
is called the Mutiara 4.
يدعى الموتيارا 4.
And I went sailing on it,
وقد أبحرت على ظهره،
and we did surveys
وأجرينا استطلاعات
throughout the southern South China sea
عبر جنوب بحر جنوب الصين
and especially the Java Sea.
وبالخصوص في بحر جاوة.
And what we caught,
وما أمسكنا به،
we didn't have words for it.
لم تكن لدينا كلمات لوصفه
What we caught, I know now,
ما أمسكنا به، أعرف الآن،
is the bottom of the sea.
هو أسفل المحيط.
And 90 percent of our catch
و90 في المئة مما أمسكنا به
were sponges,
كان إسفنجا،
other animals that are fixed on the bottom.
حيوانات أخرى مثبتة في الأسفل.
And actually most of the fish,
وفي معظم السمك في الواقع،
they are a little spot on the debris,
هي بقعة صغيرة على الحطام،
the piles of debris, were coral reef fish.
أكوام الحطام، كانت أسماك شعاب مرجانية.
Essentially the bottom of the sea came onto the deck
أسفل البحر في الأساس جاء إلى سطح المركب
and then was thrown down.
ثم تم رميه نحو الأسفل.
And these pictures are extraordinary
وهذه الصور استثنائية
because this transition is very rapid.
لأن التحول سريع للغاية.
Within a year, you do a survey
في غضون سنة، تقوم باستطلاع
and then commercial fishing begins.
ثم يبدأ الصيد التجاري.
The bottom is transformed
يتم تحويل أسفل المحيط
from, in this case, a hard bottom or soft coral
من، في هذه الحالة، قاع صلب أو شعاب مرجانية لينة
into a muddy mess.
إلى فوضى موحلة.
This is a dead turtle.
هذه سلحفاة ميتة.
They were not eaten, they were thrown away because they were dead.
لم تؤكل، تم رميها لأنها كانت ميتة.
And one time we caught a live one.
وفي إحدى المرات أمسكنا بواحدة حية.
It was not drowned yet.
لم تغرق بعد.
And then they wanted to kill it because it was good to eat.
ثم أرادوا قتلها لأنها لم تكن جيدة للأكل.
This mountain of debris
جبل الحطام هذا
is actually collected by fishers
تم في الواقع جمعها من قبل الصيادين
every time they go
في كل مرة يذهبون
into an area that's never been fished.
إلى منطقة لم يتم الصيد فيها من قبل.
But it's not documented.
لكنها لم توثق.
We transform the world,
نحن نحول العالم،
but we don't remember it.
لكننا لا نتذكر ذلك.
We adjust our baseline
نغير خط الأساس
to the new level,
إلى المستوى الجديد،
and we don't recall what was there.
ولا نتذكر ما كان هناك.
If you generalize this,
إن عممتم هذا،
something like this happens.
شيء مثل هذا يحصل.
You have on the y axis some good thing:
لدينا على محور الأراتيب أشياء جيدة:
biodiversity, numbers of orca,
التنوع البيولوجي، أرقام الأوركا،
the greenness of your country, the water supply.
اخضرار بلدكم، الموارد المائية.
And over time it changes --
ومع مرور الزمن تتغير.
it changes
تتغير
because people do things, or naturally.
لأن الناس يقومون بأشياء بطريقة طبيعية تماما.
Every generation
كل جيل
will use the images
سيستخدم الصور
that they got at the beginning of their conscious lives
التي تلقوها في بداية حياتهم الواعية
as a standard
كمعيار
and will extrapolate forward.
وسيستقرؤون تقدما.
And the difference then,
والاختلاف آنذاك،
they perceive as a loss.
يتصورون أنه خسارة.
But they don't perceive what happened before as a loss.
لكنهم لا يتصورون ما جرى من قبل على أنه خسارة.
You can have a succession of changes.
يمكن أن يكون لديك تعاقب تغيرات.
At the end you want to sustain
وفي النهاية تريد أن تتكبد
miserable leftovers.
بقايا بائسة.
And that, to a large extent, is what we want to do now.
وذلك، إلى حد كبير، هو كا نريد أن نقوم به الآن.
We want to sustain things that are gone
نريد أن نساند أشياء قد ضاعت
or things that are not the way they were.
أو الأشياء التي ليست كما كانت عليه.
Now one should think
الآن يجدر بالمرء التفكير
this problem affected people
في أن هذه المشكلة أثرت على الناس
certainly when in predatory societies,
بالتأكيد داخل المجتمعات الافتراسية،
they killed animals
قتلوا الحيوانات
and they didn't know they had done so
ولم يعرفوا أنهم قاموا بذلك
after a few generations.
بعد بضعة أجيال.
Because, obviously,
لأنه، وبوضوح،
an animal that is very abundant,
حيوان يوجد بوفرة
before it gets extinct,
قبل أن ينقرض،
it becomes rare.
يصبح نادرا.
So you don't lose abundant animals.
وبالتالي لا تفقد الحيوانات الوافرة.
You always lose rare animals.
دائما ما نفقد الحيوانات النادرة.
And therefore they're not perceived
وبالتالي لا ينظر إليها
as a big loss.
على أنها خسارة كبيرة.
Over time,
مع مرور الوقت،
we concentrate on large animals,
نركز على حيوانات كبيرة،
and in a sea that means the big fish.
وفي بحر يعني ذلك السمك الكبير.
They become rarer because we fish them.
تصير أندر لأننا نصطادها.
Over time we have a few fish left
مع مرور الوقت لدينا بضع أسماك متبقة
and we think this is the baseline.
ونظن أن هذا هو خط الأساس.
And the question is,
والسؤال هو،
why do people accept this?
لماذا يقبل الناس ذلك؟
Well because they don't know that it was different.
حسنا لأنهم لا يعرفون أنه كان مختلفا.
And in fact, lots of people, scientists,
وفي الواقع، الكثير من الناس، العلماء،
will contest that it was really different.
سيتبارون في أنه كان حقا مختلفا.
And they will contest this
وسيتبارون في هذا
because the evidence
لأن الدليل
presented in an earlier mode
المعروض في نسق سابق
is not in the way
ليس على الشاكلة
they would like the evidence presented.
التي يتم بها عرض الدليل.
For example,
على سبيل المثال،
the anecdote that some present,
الحكاية التي يقدمها البعض،
as Captain so-and-so
القبطان الفلاني
observed lots of fish in this area
راقب الكثير من الأسماك في هذه المنطقة
cannot be used
لا يمكن أن تستخدم
or is usually not utilized by fishery scientists,
أو لا تستخدم عادة من طرف علماء مصايد الأسماك،
because it's not "scientific."
لأنها ليست "علمية."
So you have a situation
إذن لديك وضعية
where people don't know the past,
حيث لا يعرف الناس الماضي،
even though we live in literate societies,
بالرغم من أننا نعيش في مجتمعات متعلمة،
because they don't trust
لأنهم لا يثقون
the sources of the past.
في موارد الماضي.
And hence, the enormous role
وبالتالي، الدور الأساسي
that a marine protected area can play.
الذي تلعبه منطقة بحرية محمية.
Because with marine protected areas,
لأنه مع المناطق البحرية المحمية،
we actually recreate the past.
نقوم في الواقع بإعادة إنشاء الماضي.
We recreate the past that people cannot conceive
نعيد إنشاء الماضي الذي لا يستطيع الناس تصوره
because the baseline has shifted
لأن خط الأساس قد انزلق
and is extremely low.
وهو في غاية الدنو.
That is for people
هذا بالنسبة للناس
who can see a marine protected area
الذين يمكن أن يروا منطقة بحرية محمية
and who can benefit
والذين يمكن أن يستفيدوا
from the insight that it provides,
من الرؤى التي توفرها،
which enables them to reset their baseline.
والتي تسمح لهم بإعادة تشكيل خط أساسهم.
How about the people who can't do that
ماذا عن الناس الذين لا يمكنهم القيام بذلك
because they have no access --
لأنهم لا يستطيعون الوصول إلى --
the people in the Midwest for example?
الناس في الغرب الأوسط على سبيل المثال؟
There I think
هناك أعتقد
that the arts and film
أن الفن والفيلم
can perhaps fill the gap,
يمكن ربما أن تعبئ الفجوة،
and simulation.
والمحاكاة.
This is a simulation of Chesapeake Bay.
هذه محاكاة لخليج تشيسبايك.
There were gray whales in Chesapeake Bay a long time ago --
كانت هناك حيتان رمادية في خليج تشيسبايك قبل وقت طويل --
500 years ago.
قبل 500 سنة.
And you will have noticed that the hues and tones
وستلاحظون أن الأشكال والنغمات
are like "Avatar."
هي مثل "أفاتار"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And if you think about "Avatar,"
وحين تفكرون بخصوص "أفاتار"،
if you think of why people were so touched by it --
حيت تفكرون لماذا كان الناس متأثرين عاطفيا بذلك --
never mind the Pocahontas story --
لا تهتموا بقصة بوكاهونتاس --
why so touched by the imagery?
لماذا يتأثرون للغاية من الصور؟
Because it evokes something
لأنها تستحضر شيئا
that in a sense has been lost.
التي بمعنى ما قد فقدت.
And so my recommendation,
وبالتالي توصيتي،
it's the only one I will provide,
هي الوحيدة التي سأقدم،
is for Cameron to do "Avatar II" underwater.
هي لكامرون أن ينتج "أفاتار 2" تحت الماء.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)